There are many lies that we
are told by business gurus
when we first start trying
to make money online.
You must do sales calls,
you must be DMing people or hanging
out in Facebook groups.
But one of the worst lies we're told
is that you must niche
down and that the riches
are in the niches.
And many of you watching this might think
that if you're going to do well in life
or online or on social media,
whatever it is,
that you need to understand and niche
and zone in on that, and you don't.
One of the biggest examples we've seen of
this recently would be this clip.
If you're a lesbian
and you're struggling with certain food
cravings when you're on
a diet, like these cookies,
I'm going to tell you why you should be
eating
these foods more.
Now,
I'm not sure who this woman's business
coach is, and they've gone, "Oh, do you
know what?
I think you should be your avatar.
So therefore, if you're a lesbian,
you should only work with lesbians."
Fantastic.
Great.
Maybe there's different calorie amounts in
rug munching, I don't know.
But why I think this
is a terrible idea
and terrible advice to anyone that's going
to consider this is the solution isn't any
different based on sexuality, or I
haven't seen any evidence to insinuate
that.
So niching into something as trivial as
that is the same as me going, "I've got
some great business advice for people
that are left-handed." That's just
ridiculous, it doesn't make any sense.
It's idiotic, in fact.
Because there could be plenty of
heterosexual women
that she could be perfect for.
And that's the thing,
the majority of people are heterosexual.
So she's just cutting down the pool of
people that she can do work with to
this very small subset based off the
insinuation that if she goes niche,
they'll do business with her like,
"Oh my God,
this is what I've been waiting for,
a fat loss coach that is lesbian." Now,
niching in some respects can be
good,
but first what we need to understand,
we don't actually want a niche.
What we want to understand
is something called an avatar.
And an avatar isn't a blue person
that you might have seen in the movies
online.
An avatar is the person in which you
are trying to communicate to.
You might have noticed this on TV,
for instance.
If you watch an advert for a Range Rover,
even the voice, "Head down to your
local Range Rover dealership to see the
new offers that we're doing on the Vogue."
They even talk like the person they're
trying to attract.
Maybe if you're going to go buy a pickup
truck, it would be, "Hello, mate, get down
to your local dealer
and see what four-by-four deals we've got
going on for you."
Even the voices in which they use. Again,
when you look at different colors on
websites,
it's in line with the avatar
which they're going after.
You might see more feminine colors
when going after women,
maybe more masculine
colors when going after men, et cetera.
So a lot of our messaging
and a lot of our strategy online
is about attracting the
right people,
but it's not about pushing away the wrong
people.
For instance,
I've worked with probably 60%,
70% women in my life since running a
fitness business.
That's over 100,000 people through my
training app.
I never said, "If you're a man,
don't even bother. I don't train men.
If you've got a dick,
you're not coming in." I
was just talking the language of,
"Hey, if you want to drop a dress size.
Hey,
if you want to feel more confident in the
clothes that you used to wear.
Hey,
maybe you put something on this week
that didn't fit like it used to fit a
couple of months ago." I'm talking to a
certain avatar, but I'm not excluding
people from doing business with me.
Similarly to when I'm making videos on
YouTube right now.
The majority of my audience,
personal trainers, fitness businesses,
yoga
instructors, golf instructors,
jujitsu gym owners.
But by keeping the topics relevant
and kind of broader to other subjects.
If you are a chef
that wants to take your business online,
I'm not going to
say, "Well, you're not a fitness coach.
Get out." If anything, I'd say, "Well,
most of what I teach to personal trainers
would apply to you. And if anything,
your demographic and opportunity online, I
think is far superior to
that of a personal trainer." Because in
the UK, what, 16%
of people have a gym membership,
but guess what percentage of the UK eats?
Everyone. Now,
when it comes to kind of mastering the art
of pushing people away,
bringing them in,
we really should look at a term called
polarization.
Now,
polarization is something slightly
different, which I do 100% lean
on when it comes to brand building
and generally just creating waves on
social
media.
Although we do want to communicate to the
right type of person, and we
certainly don't want to push people away
for no reason, especially if they're going
to be able to make a good impact to our
business and we're going to make a good
impact to their lives.
We should probably tactically find some
cohorts of people
that we don't want to agree with.
For instance, if you're a butcher's, you
shouldn't give a flying fuck about the
opinions of vegetarians or vegans.
Therefore,
in the beginning of your content,
you could be like, "Here's a really
good barbecue recipe that the vegans
are going to lose sleep about."
And the vegans
will be like, "Ugh."
But you were never going to sell it to
them in the first place, the same way
that I
rip into bodybuilders. I say, "Cool,
if you want to not eat for six
months and step on stage in fake tan
and put on a pair of Speedos to impress
another bunch of dudes
and not call it gay
and call it bodybuilding instead, nice
one, brother." And the bodybuilders
are like, "Ugh,
what do you know?" They say
I've got a mid-rig,
or they take the piss out of my haircut,
whatever.
But bodybuilders are never going to join
my fitness app.
Neither are vegans, neither
are any of the people
that I call out online.
A lot of the intentional controversy
and the intentional contrarianism in which
I have online is to polarize the right
types of people, especially those that are
never going to do business with me.
I've often said,
and I've even put in my books, that
if you were to invite me to
your family barbecue and they
were talking about Formula 1. I love cars.
I'm a bit of a petrolhead.
I just don't really like Formula 1.
If someone was like, "Oh, James,
did you see the Singapore Grand Prix at
the
weekend? What did you think?" I'd go,
"Do you know what, mate?
I kind of think Formula 1's a bit shit."
Now, to the majority of people there,
they'd go, "This guy's a knobhead."
But there could be two
or three people that go,
"Do you know what, James? Formula 1
is shit. Do you want a beer?
Come here." You can't be vanilla with
everyone.
You do have to pick your sides,
and being a contrarian
is one way to get ahead,
especially when it comes to positioning
your brand.
One of the biggest issues that I had
that I try and help other people with is,
for
instance, most personal trainers
are crippled with not being able to post
content
because they're worried about what other
personal trainers are going to think.
They're the only people that
are never going to do business with them.
Same with online chefs putting out
recipes. "Oh, no.
What are other people in the field going
to..." They're never going to do business
with you.
I was working with a German in the Discord
today who's like the German
Ali Abdaal. I said, "Bro,
you should be looking at Ali Abdaal's best
titles and
thumbnails and making your own versions in
German." He goes, "Yeah, but you get
called out for that in Germany." By who,
bro? By who?
People that are never going to buy your
fucking product. Get on with it.
So when it comes to connecting with your
avatar, you don't just say, "Hey, if
you're between 5'8" and 5'9"
and you're left-handed and you
were born on the island
of Guernsey,
then I've got a solution for you." That's
not how we communicate.
We do not niche down to try
and get someone to go, "Oh my God,
that's me." The best
way you can communicate with someone
is to understand their problems.
That's what we're doing on social media.
This is your biggest lesson you can ever
learn. No one gives a fuck about you.
Like literally,
no one gives a flying fuck about you.
All they care about is themselves.
Sounds harsh, but it's true.
The quicker you can understand that,
the better.
I'm going to say it one more time.
No one gives a flying fuck about anything
you do. They just care about themselves.
But if you can solve someone's problems
and continually solve someone's problems,
over a while, they'll start to like you.
But they won't like you for who you are.
They'll like you because you solved their
problems.
You might even watch this video right now
and go, "James, you're a legend.
Oh, James,
better-looking in real life."
But the truth-...
truth is,
if I stopped turning up on a constant
basis to solve your problems, we
wouldn't have the relationship
that we have right now in this video.
Everything is about give and take.
That's just how humans are.
Even people that donate money to charity,
they don't really do it because they care
about kids in Africa.
They do it because it makes them feel
better, and they do it
because it attributes status to them with
their fellow peers in the
philanthropic parts of the world.
"Oh, yes, Jordan,
you gave a million to the kids in Africa.
Oh, well done there,
sir." Everyone's just doing things to make
themselves feel
better. Back to the point.
When you can understand
that people don't give a shit
about your workout, what you did,
what weight you lost,
or anything like that, they
just care about the information
that you have that they might need,
the better you
can get on with it.
Then you can start solving their problems.
That's what every single piece of social
media content is.
If you go look at the titles
and thumbnails of all the videos in this
YouTube video
thread on my channel,
they're all solving problems,
with the occasional promotion
of some of my products.
Got to make a living.
That's what content is.
It's not a vlog.
It's not what you did on a holiday.
It's solving problems.
And the better you understand your avatar,
the better you can solve problems, and
after a while,
a niche will kind of find itself within
that.
Now, don't get me wrong.
If I get a leak in my bathroom tomorrow,
and I wake up and
I go on Google going,
"I need a plumber nearby."
And four come up, and three of
them are just plumbers,
and then there's one plumber that's a
specialist in leaky
bathrooms. Sure.
I'm probably going to pay him even
if he's a little bit more.
Or her. Could be a female plumber.
Don't be a bigot.
But ultimately,
you'd have to be pretty daft to learn all
of the things you need to
learn to be a plumber to then only work on
leaky bathrooms. You know what I mean?
I had this one guy in the Discord
that wanted to help people in Brisbane
that were
CEOs. I was like,
"Why do they have to be a CEO?" They could
be a CFO, chief
financial officer,
chief marketing officer. Jesus.
They could be a director.
They could be on the board.
They could be the owner of the business
that doesn't
necessarily call themself the chief
executive officer.
It could be a female
that owns her own flipping salon and
is making wedge, or a
dude that's a bricklayer.
All of these people have the disposable
income to be
perfect as a high achiever
that you want to go after,
but by making it a CEO and
trying to make yourself sound like a cool
corporate trainer dude, you've just
eradicated so many people
that could've been perfect for you.
"My name's James,
and I train CEOs." Just changing that to
business owner, high-functioning adult,
whatever it is, you get to
tap into such a larger cohort of the same
people.
You're going after the same people again.
There was a lady that I was working with.
She was saying she wanted to help nurses
on night shifts, and I said, "Okay.
As far as the amount of women that
are nurses that do night shift,
we're looking at
a very small amount. And also, nurses,
they're just trying to survive.
They're doing a great job.
They don't really get paid enough for the
job, so
disposable income, spare time,
spare energy.
You're going after a cohort of people
that are just tired and underpaid.
The amount of them that
are going to be able to afford you for a
12-week program
may be minimal." But either way,
why not just go after a segment of
sleep-deprived women?
Bring mothers into it,
because the problems that a
nurse faces and the problems
that a woman postpartum
face are very similar. Obviously,
not to undermine the implications of
certain
things that a woman would have to see a
female health physio about, maybe a
prolapse, blah, blah, blah, whatever,
but ultimately, sleep deprivation,
prioritizing other people over yourself.
The solutions are very much the same.
An empathetic training program,
not smashing the shit out of someone,
making sure
that you give them slow,
steady deficits or training progressions,
whatever.
But by going after nurses, again,
the amount of women that
are sleep-deprived that
need to put themselves first,
that need to get in better shape, massive.
Going after just sleep-deprived nurses,
you're going after such a small subset,
it's just completely moronic.
So instead of focusing on niches,
you should be
focusing on problems.
The cohort of people
that you want to go after share the same
problem. It's not
that they're all fucking lesbians
or they all have the same
job or the same job title,
because ultimately,
eventually you're going to
throw a call to action in front of
someone,
and they're going to respond on that
based on the amount of problems
that you've solved for that person.
Similar to this video. If this
is the first video of mine you've watched,
and I go,
"Hey, guys,
there's links in the descriptions,
and there's a buy Friday." You're
like, "Mate,
you haven't solved enough of my problems."
But if you were to watch
10, 15, 20 of these videos over weeks,
days, months, whatever, ultimately you go,
"Do you know what?
Every time James drops a video,
he solves one of my problems.
Therefore,
I'm probably going to take him up on the
offer of his email 30 Days and
30 Ways," or it's called whatever it is.
Because you're going to do business with
the person who understands your problems
the best because they have the solutions
to them.
I don't want to be spoken to you going,
"Are you a 98-kilogram, six-foot lad that
does jujitsu, used to play rugby,
and..." No, I don't want that.
I want someone to talk to me on a personal
level, and if you can do that to other
people,
they will respond to your call to actions.
They'll give you their email addresses,
they'll read your emails, and then
eventually they'll move through your sales
process to the point that they end up
doing business with you.
And quickly on that,
even though this isn't the video,
stop being so bland.
If you want to niche down,
do it with your squeezes,
your lead magnets, not with your brand.
"I help men between 39 and 42." Instead,
if you want to niche, do it on
your lead magnet.
One of the best ones
that I think I shared with someone the
other
day was if you said,
"If you're someone
that wants to go for a leisurely jog with
your top off but you feel too insecure
about how you look shirtless, do
this." Because the times I've been
happiest with my physique,
I've gone for topless
runs, and all the other times
that I've not been happy with my physique,
I couldn't
imagine anything worse. If I
was to see that, I'd go,
"This person knows me and
understands me." One of the first hooks
that captured me as a
personal trainer to join the first course
that I went to, I remember it vividly.
It said, "Are you overworked, underpaid,
tired, and frustrated?" Now,
that didn't have to just mean a personal
trainer.
That could apply to so many businesses.
As soon as I saw that, boom,
this person knows my problems.
Became a client.
So many people think they need to niche
down and have a niche, and you don't.
You need to be very good at
problem-solving, and ultimately,
you're going to have a
skill set.
Work to the problems you solve the best.
Again, you only need like 30
or 40 people to do business with you for
you to make a
lot of money. And that
is why niching too much can keep you poor.
Again,
I don't know what YouTube puts here,
but it thinks, and YouTube's a pretty
smart bugger, that if you watch that,
that you'll become even more of a smart
bugger. So that's going to be there.
Feel free to click that, and again,
there are going to be three links in the
description. And yeah,
if I've solved enough of your problems,
click them, brother.
And if not,
then just watch the next video. Or don't.
I'm not your dad.